<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
<string name="cat_group_title">Group Name</string>
<string name="cat_group_desc">This is an arbitrary name; categories with the same group will 
appear in a list on the same page.  For example, you may want to have categories such as "weight" 
and "exercise" under the group of "health," and the categories of "driving time" and "gas used" 
under the group of "auto."</string>
<string name="cat_category_title">Category Name</string>
<string name="cat_category_desc">Name of the data to be tracked.</string>
<string name="cat_default_value_title">Default Value</string>
<string name="cat_default_value_desc">Once a category is added, it will appear in a list on 
the main screen. This is the value that will filled in by default, so if there's a particular 
value that you tend to enter more frequently than others, feel free to set it here.</string>
<string name="cat_synthetic_title">Synthetic</string>
<string name="cat_synthetic_desc">Synthetic series are based on the inputs of
one or more other series, such as adding two series together or referencing the previous
timestamp or value of a series.  No data is stored in the database, however, synthetic
values are present when exporting.</string>
<string name="cat_formula_title">Default Value</string>
<string name="cat_formula_desc">(TODO)</string>
<string name="cat_increment_title">Increment/Decrement</string>
<string name="cat_increment_desc">When recording an entry under a category, the value can 
be entered directly via the keyboard.  However, depending on the user interface selection in 
"Settings," there may be a set of plus and minus buttons near the text entry.  The value in 
this box controls how much the value in the text entry box is changed with one click of 
either button.</string>
<string name="cat_goal_title">Goal</string>
<string name="cat_goal_desc">If there is a goal, such as reaching a weight of 150 pounds, 
enter it here.  This will allow the graph to display a goal line for the category, and is used 
by the trend icons displayed in the category list to determine if you are moving to or away 
from your goal.
</string>
<string name="cat_color_title">Color</string>
<string name="cat_color_desc">The color has no effect on the operation of application, 
but makes the list of categories easier to differentiate.  Each category will also be graphed 
in this color.
</string>
<string name="cat_type_title">Type</string>
<string name="cat_type_desc">The value type determines how multiple entries are aggregated,
both in data input (where multiple entries within the same period listed below will be aggregated
into a single point) and during graphing, where value may be temporarily aggregated for the purpose
of display only.  An example may prove to illustrate the difference most effectively:  suppose you 
are tracking the number of hours exercised per day.  In this case, if you worked out an hour in 
the morning and and hour in the evening, you'd want the total for the day to be 2 hours, do you'd 
choose "Sum."  However, if  you're tracking your weight, and you weighed yourself in the morning and 
evening, you'd want the two values to be averaged together, so you'd choose "Average."  Note that this 
setting only really makes a difference if and aggregation level other than "None" is selected below.
</string>
<string name="cat_aggregate_title">Aggregation</string>
<string name="cat_aggregate_desc">If you'd like to collapse multiple entries into one, 
select the period that you'd like to collapse.  See description in Value Type for an example.  
Note that once entries are aggregated, they cannot be separated, and the timestamp of the entry 
will be that of the first entry added in the period.  Aggregating by period will minimize the 
amount of data that needs to be stored.  This field can be changed at any time, and only affect 
entries that are added after the last time this field is changed -- i.e., if you select "Day", 
add some entries, and then change the category to "Hour", all the previous entries will still 
be aggregated into days, and the new entries moving forward will be aggregated into hours.
</string>
<string name="cat_interp_title">Interpolation</string>
<string name="cat_interp_desc">This field controls how data between entries are interpolated,
which affects data correlation and graphing.</string>
<string name="cat_zerofill_title">Zero Empty Periods</string>
<string name="cat_zerofill_desc">Have EvenTrend automatically insert 0's at for each aggregation
period that passes without any entries.  The addition will occur at the start of the period, and
if any entries are added later on within the period, the 0 will be updated to reflect the new value.  
An example may help to explain this better: say you're trying to quit smoking, and are 
recording the number of cigarettes consumed per day, you'd probably want to set the Aggregation 
to "Day", and select this option.  For any days in which you didn't have any cigarettes, 
a 0 would be automatically inserted.  However, if you were tracking your weight, you probably 
wouldn't want to select this:  if you miss weighing yourself one day, you just 
want to ignore the period instead of recording a weight of 0.  Note that this option is only available
if the type is "Sum" and the aggregation period is not "None."
</string>
<string name="calendar_overview">
Data Range info is only calculated over all the displayed data.  The solid color 
at the top of the box indicates the trend going toward or away from the goal compared to the previous
day, and the color of the value in the box denotes wether the trend was going toward or away from the
goal compared to the previous day.  Brighter colors indicate a larger change, dimmer colors a smaller
change, and gray indicates that the value was essentially flat (as determined by the sensitivity
preferences.)
</string>
<string name="formula_help">
Note:  formulas may be considered an advanced feature of this program.

Formulas may be constructed of binary operations only, that is, of the form \'x operator y\', and
must evaluate to a series of values.  For example, \'series "water" + series "beers"\' and 
\'40 - series "work hours"\' both evaluate to a sequence, while \'4 + 5\' does not.  A series must
consist of the word \'series\' followed by whitespace and the name of the category to use in double
quotes, as in the examples presented above.

There is no implicit 
grouping, so instead of attempting to calculate \'x + y + z\', the following should be used:  
\'(x + y) + z\' or \'x + (y + z)\'.  The following operations are supported:  \'+\', \'-\', \'*\', \'/\', and 
\'previous\'.  The last operator deserves special comment:  it returns the difference of each value or 
timestamp in the series with the one preceding it.  For example, if the series were called \'weight\', 
and the values [150, 153, 147] had been entered over time, the equation \'series "weight" previous value\'
would evaluate to [0, 3, -6].  If each datum in the series was entered precisely 1 day apart,
the equation \'series "weight" previous value\' would yield [0, 86400000, 86400000] - this is because
the timestamp of each entry is measured in milliseconds.  Because of this, some helpful constants
are provided:  \'minute\', \'hour\', \'am/pm\', \'day\', \'week\', \'month\', \'quarter\', and \'year\', which are
defined as the average number of milliseconds in each periods' time.  So, in order to calculate 
how many hours between weighings, the following may be used: 
\'(series "weight" previous timestamp) / hour\'.
\n
</string>
<string name="overview">
EvenTrend is a program to track arbitrary data over time.  In short, you can create categories 
of data, graph multiple items at one time, look at the historical trend, and compare it against 
goals.  It's intended to be able to add data incrementally as it occurs with a minimum of clicks 
or presses.

The first step in using EvenTrend to the create a category, for example, "weight." To 
create a category, click the "Menu" button from the main screen and select "Add Category." 
After a category is created, it will be listed on the main screen.  Whenever there's and event 
that you want to record occurs, launch EvenTrend, set the value, and click "Add."

There are are a lot of fields that can be filled out when creating a category.  Click on each
the text of each field when adding a category for help.

Brief notes on other aspects of EvenTrend:

When viewing a category list, long clicks or the trackball can be used the select categories 
for re-ordering or editing.

In order to save or restore a EvenTrend database, select "Edit Entries" from the main menu, 
and then select "Export to Mail," "Export to File," or "Restore."  "Export to File" will store 
a comma separated value dump of the databses to the sdcard of your phone under the directory 
"EvenTrend."  "Restore" reads one of these CSV files from the same directory and will 
replace all the current data.

Graph aggregation only affect the display of the data, and is distinct from the aggregation set 
for the category.  The trending used in the graph is an exponentially weighted moving average 
based on the history value set in the preferences.  This essentially means that recent entries 
are weighted more heavily than older entries, and with the default smoothing constant of 0.1, 
using a history value greater than 20 is not of any use.  The "sensitivity" preferences is a 
multiplier on the standard deviation history of the series:  if the current trend datapoint is
greater than or less than the last trend point by (standard deviation * sensitivity), a "big up"
or "big down" arrow will be displayed, else the "little up," "little down," or "flat" arrow will 
be displayed. 
</string>
<string name="prefs_overview">
Default Group:  this is the group the display by default, however, since android programs are
essentially "always running," this only takes effect if the program has been killed and restarted
by the system.
\n
Graph Background:  black or white.  Most development has been done with a black screen, since I
think it's a little easier on the eyes, and minimizes battery use, so the white background might
look a little funky.
\n
Decimal Places:  the number of decimal places to round values to.  This is used throughout the
application.  Default is 2.
\n
Note that changes to the next three fields will only manifest once a new data point has been
added to a series, or if the "Recalc Trends" menu item is selected.
\n
History:  the number of datapoints to take into account when calculating trends and other statistics.
Default value is 20, and with a default smoothing percentage of 10% (0.1), there is no reason to
make it larger.
\n
Standard Deviation Sensitivity:  On the main screen, trend icons are selected based on the difference
of the current trend and the trend value at the previous data point.  The threshold for determining the
incline of arrow is the standard deviation * this value.  So, With a this value set to 1.0,
this means that a change of greater than 1 standard deviation (over the last "History" datapoints)
will result in a trend icon that points 45 degrees up or down, and an arrow that points slightly up
or down if the change exceeds 1/2 a standard deviation.  If the value is 0.5, that means the arrow 
will be set to 45 degrees up or down at 1/2 a standard deviation, and slightly up or down at 1/4 a 
standard deviation.  On the calendar views, this has a similar function related to the intensity of 
the green or red color of value and trend changes.  Default is 1.0.
\n
Smoothing Constant:  This is a value indicating the weight of previous datapoints to the current
one.  The formula is defined as trend(n) = trend(n-1) + (smoothing) * (value(n) - trend(n-1)).  Thus,
a value of 1.0 indicates that a strict average of the last "History" points will be taken.  Anything
less than 1.0 indicates that recent points have more influence over the trend than previous points,
and the smaller the value, the more important recent data is.  Default is 0.1.
\n
</string>
</resources>